Guide to the John Jackson McSwain papers, 1910-1941 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
John Jackson McSwain papers 1910-1941 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
McSwain, John Jackson, 1875-1936
8.8 Linear Feet Approx. 6600 Items
Lawyer, Army officer, and U.S. Representative from Greenville, South Carolina.
Collection largely consists of letters from McSwain's constituents (1921-1936). Subjects discussed include McSwain's participation in World War I; South Carolina and national politics; South Carolina economic conditions, especially cotton farming and manufacturing; the University of South Carolina and the Citadel (circa 1920-1936); Prohibition; New Deal politics and McSwain's changing attitude toward President Roosevelt; McSwain's advocacy of a strong Air Force, and his activities on Congressional committees; and William Randolph Hearst's dislike of McSwain. Other documents refer to McSwain's political office and includes many speeches, writings, and printed material, including many clippings and political and military publications. There are also papers relating to Dixon R. Davis, McSwain's private secretary and later postmaster of Greenville, S.C., and Joseph Raleigh Bryson, McSwain's successor in the House of Representatives. Correspondents include Henry H. Arnold, Newton D. Baker, Cole L. Blease, Johnson Hagood, Gabriel Haywood Mahon, Oscar K. Mauldin, Dwight Whitney Morrow, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Charles Pelot Summerall, and Harry Hines Woodring.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The John Jackson McSwain papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1954.
Collection Overview
Collection largely consists of letters from John Jackson McSwain's constituents, dating from 1921 to 1936. Subjects discussed include McSwain's participation in World War I; South Carolina and national politics; South Carolina economic conditions, especially cotton farming and manufacturing; the University of South Carolina and the Citadel (circa 1920-1936); prohibition; New Deal politics and McSwain's changing attitude toward President Roosevelt; McSwain's advocacy of a strong Air Force, and his activities on Congressional committees; and William Randolph Hearst's dislike of McSwain.
The correspondence starts with a few letters from 1910, when McSwain began to take tentative steps towards politics. There are letters relating to Dr. James Woodrow, Sept.2, 1910; and to Woodrow Wilson's campaigns for Governor of New Jersey in 1910 and for the presidency in 1912. There are patronage letters in 1912 and 1913, and a cloth portrait of Woodrow Wilson woven at Clemson College, South Carolina, in 1915.
Other documents refer to McSwain's political office and includes speeches, writings, and printed material, including many clippings and political and military publications. There are also papers relating to Dixon R. Davis, McSwain's private secretary and later postmaster of Greenville, S.C., and Joseph Raleigh Bryson, McSwain's successor in the House of Representatives. Correspondents include Henry H. Arnold, Newton D. Baker, Cole L. Blease, Johnson Hagood, Gabriel Haywood Mahon, Oscar K. Mauldin, Dwight Whitney Morrow, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Charles Pelot Summerall, and Harry Hines Woodring. The latest dates refer to condolences sent following McSwain's death of a heart attack in 1936, and his secretary Dixon Davis's political maneuverings with Joseph Raleigh Bryson following this event.
The digitized cardfiles provide a very detailed discussion of the collection's contents and topics. For access, please consult with a reference archivist.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Bryson, Joseph Raleigh, 1893-1953
Citadel, the Military College of South Carolina
Davis, Dixon R.
Hearst, William Randolph, 1863-1951
McSwain, John Jackson, 1875-1936
New Deal, 1933-1939
Natural resources -- United States
Prohibition -- United States
South Carolina -- Economic conditions
South Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950
United States -- Economic conditions
United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century
Universities and colleges -- South Carolina
University of South Carolina
World War, 1914-1918 -- Participation, American
Scrapbooks
Related Material
William Watts Ball papers, 1778-1952 and undated (contains correspondence from John Jackson McSwain)
Rubenstein Library
Description of Collection
- John Jackson McSwain Papers, 1875-1936 and undated, (22 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1910-1923 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1924-1926 Mar. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1926 Apr.-Dec. (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1927-1928 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1929-1932 Mar. (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1932 Apr.-July 12 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1932 July 13-Dec. (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1933-1934 Apr. 13 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1934 Apr. 14-June (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1934 July-1935 Mar. 15 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1935 Mar. 16-1936 Feb. 3 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1936 Feb. 4-Apr. 10 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1936 Apr. 11-Sept. 26 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, 1937-1941, (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - Candidate expenditures, 1930-1935 (Box 14)
  - Addresses and writings, 1917-1934, (3 folders) (Box 14)
  - Addresses and writings, 1935-1936, (3 folders) (Box 15)
  - Lists of persons in the 4th Congressional District, (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Lists of persons in the 4th Congressional District (Box 16)
  - Lists of persons in the 4th Congressional District, (5 folders) (Box 17)
  - Petitions, lists, affidavits, 1911-1932 (Box 17)
  - Congressional Resolutions and Bills, pamphlets, speeches, programs, political leaflets (Box 18)
  - Clippings, 1924-1938 (Box 19)
  - Clippings, 1924-1938 (Box 20)
  - Clippings, 1924-1938 (Box 21)
  - 21st Annual Report of National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics, 1935 (Box 22)
  - Individual voting record by roll call for the 68th-69th and 71st-74th Congresses, 1923-1937 (Box 22)
  - Notes, undated (Box 22)
  - Scrapbook, 1921-1924, (95 pages) (Volume F:5719)
  - Scrapbook, 1922-1924, (48 pages) (Volume L:5720)
  - Scrapbook, 1923-1927, (143 pages) (Volume L:5721)
  - Scrapbook, 1927-1932, (144 pages) (Volume L:5722)
  - Scrapbook, 1932-1935, (142 pages) (Volume F:5723)
  - Lists of Names, 1921-1924, (132 pages) (Volume L:5724)
  - Lists of Names, 1931-1932, (172 pages) (Volume L:5725)